Second Dish
Episode 9
THE 43rd AUTUMN
SELECTION
Grand Finale
What?!
（４人）ひいいいいい！
What the hell is that?
（青木大吾(あおきだいご)）何だ あれ？
（佐藤昭二(さとうしょうじ)）なまくら刀？
A dull blade?
The transfer student's done something weird again.
（男子生徒Ａ）
編入生のヤツ
また おかしなことを
Did he give up the fight?
（男子生徒Ｂ）
試合捨ててんのかぁ？
I see.
（葉山(はやま)アキラ）なるほどな
So that's why you didn't come to the fish market this morning.
今朝 魚河岸に来なかったのは
そういうことか 幸平
（幸平創真(ゆきひらそうま)）おっ？
Huh?
You chose aging as a way to compensate for the difference in ingredient quality.
素材の差を埋めるために
お前が選んだ手は 熟成
I could tell what you used to age the fish just by looking at it.
（黒木場(くろきば)リョウ）
見ただけで何を使って
熟成したのか すぐ分かったぜ
But that's not enough to reach the best of what the season has to offer.
だが その程度じゃ
旬の新鮮さには届かねえ
You won't know that for sure until you eat it.
（創真）
そんなの食ってみなきゃ
分かんねえだろ？
I'll cook enough for you guys to try too.
料理は お前らの分も
用意してやっから
Yeah, right.
ふざけるな
もう勝負はついた
The outcome's already clear.
Congratulations on finishing third.
（葉山）
３位入賞 おめでとう
十分誇っていい成績だぜ
That's good enough to be rightfully proud.
（創真）ん？
Honored guests, the time for the Autumn Selection Grand Finale to begin is almost here!
（一色慧(いっしきさとし)）
ご来場の皆様 秋の選抜決勝戦
開始時間が迫ってまいりました
Please look up at the ceiling!
天井にご注目ください
（観客の歓声）
Wow!
（男子生徒Ｃ）
すげえ～！
天井が割れていくぞ！
The ceiling's splitting open!
Soon.
間もなくだ
This is Gatten Hall as it truly is.
これが“月天(がってん)の間”の
真の姿…
（観客のどよめき）
The cooking time in the grand finale will span approximately two hours.
（一色）
決勝戦の調理時間は
およそ２時間
This is the time it takes from the moment the moon appears in full,
月が完全に現れた瞬間から
天の道を渡り終え―
traverses across the skies,
and becomes hidden once more.
再び姿を隠すまでとします
（堂島銀(どうじまぎん)）
フッフ…　毎年恒例とはいえ
大仰なことですな
Though it's the same every year,
it's still quite a spectacle.
I fondly remember those days.
（堂島）
思い出す 懐かしき日々を
That night when I fought
in the Autumn Selection grand finale....
自分が選抜の決勝を戦った
あの夜を
All the chefs who have ever stood on this stage
この舞台に立った
すべての料理人が―
have seen the same moon.
同じ月を見てきたのだ
Don't lose to anyone else
until you lose to me again next time!
（幸平城一郎(ゆきひらじょういちろう)）
次に俺に負けるまで
誰にも負けんじゃねえぜ
I'm gonna gun for the top seat
among Tohtsuki's first-years!
（創真）獲りにいく
遠月(とおつき)１年最強の座！
Ready!
（薙切仙左衛門(なきりせんざえもん)）
構えよ！
Let the cooking...
（仙左衛門）調理
begin!
開始ぃ～！
♪～
omoiegaiteru imeeji yori haruka mukou gawa e
Far beyond the image I have in my mind
tsukuriagete yuku shinjitsu wa mada tooku
The reality I'm building up is still far away
hatenai tabiji
An endless journey
otagai no puraido wo togisumaseyou ze
Let's hone each other's pride
kotoba nante kazari wa hadakesaserya ii
Make people see that words are cheap and unimportant
butsukariai migakarete iku
We fight each other and hone our skills
Rolling stone
deai wa shockwave shockwave
Our encounters cause shockwaves
mada shiranai sekai e
We're reckless challengers
arukihajimeta mubou na chousensha sa
Heading toward a world as yet unexplored
te ni shita yaiba de ashita wo
With the blade in your hand
kirihirakeba iin darou
Open the way to the future
dareka no mon ja nai jibun dake no story
This is my story and no one else's
Cause we're still rough diamonds on the road
～♪
A SWORD THAT SIGNALS AUTUMN
None of the candidates have
touched their Pacific saury.
（堂島）
どの選手もまだ―
サンマには
手をつけないな
They'll start by prepping their other ingredients. Typical, I suppose.
他の素材から下処理を進める
定石どおりか
Working the fish more than necessary will negatively impact its freshness.
余計な手数は 魚の鮮度を
落とすことにつながる
They have to maintain the fish's freshness as much as possible.
可能な限り 新鮮さを
保たなければならぬからな
（薙切(なきり)レオノーラ）
ウフフ… 何だか
エキサイトしてきたです 私
I'm being excited, yes.
Watching young men...
This is sight for hurting eyes.
若い男の子見るのこと
この上なき眼福(がんぷく)ですよ
Oh, Mother, you're being rather inappropriate.
（薙切(なきり)アリス）
まあ お母様ったら
何だか淫(みだ)ら
And your vocabulary is skewed, as usual.
それに相変わらず
語彙(ごい)に偏りが
Alice!
（薙切(なきり)えりな）
アリス！
客席に戻りなさいってば！
Go back to your seat in the audience!
Erina, you should come over here too!
えりなもこっちへ
来ればいいのに
She can, can't she, Grandfather?
ねっ いいでしょう
おじい様？
Yes. It doesn't matter.
うむ 構わん
See, Erina?
ほーら！　えりなったら～
ハハハ 楽しいご家族だなぁ
薙切君
What a fun family, Nakiri-kun.
Oh?
おや？ 幸平がサンマに
手をつけたようだぞ
Yukihira seems to be handling his Pacific saury.
Maybe the aging was a success?
（榊涼子(さかきりょうこ)）
熟成は成功したのかしら？
Yeah. What kind of dish will he make with it?
（丸井善二(まるいぜんじ)）
ああ
そして一体どんな料理を作る？
Kurokiba Ryou. Hayama Akira.
（伊武崎峻(いぶさきしゅん)）
黒木場リョウ　葉山アキラ
Can you win against those two monsters, Yukihira?
あのバケモノ２人に
勝てるのか？
幸平！
Ah!
（大泉柿之進(おおいずみかきのしん)）
おおおっ！
So many different seafood ingredients on the young Kurokiba's prep surface!
黒木場少年の調理台には
数々の魚介が！
I also see ripe tomatoes and olive oil.
それに完熟したトマトに
オリーブオイル
He probably intends to make acqua pazza.
（早乙女星周(さおとめせいしゅう)）
恐らく彼は アクアパッツアを
作るつもりですね
Acqua pazza is a regional dish from Southern Italy.
（堂島）アクアパッツア
南イタリアで生まれた
郷土料理だな
With fish as the main ingredient, many other ingredients are simmered into a stew.
魚を中心に 様々な具材を
まとめて煮込んで作る―
It's a simple yet dynamic dish.
シンプルかつ豪快な一品だ
It's traditional to use olive oil,
tomatoes, and shellfish.
オリーブオイルとトマト
それに貝類を入れるのが定番です！
It's also notable that the dish doesn't use much in the way of seasoning.
調味料をあまり使わないのも
特徴ですね
Because of its simplicity, the quality of its ingredients comes to the fore.
シンプルだからこそ
素材の良しあしがストレートに出る
It's a great dish to showcase his ability to judge his ingredients.
彼の目利きを生かすのに
うってつけの料理だわ
But each and every ingredient is strong enough to be the main player.
（大泉）
しかしどの食材も
味の主役を張れるものばかり
Wouldn't blindly boiling them down together
あれらを一緒くたに
煮込んでは―
actually eclipse the Pacific saury's strengths?
サンマの良さが
霞(かす)んでしまうのではないか？
True, and the Pacific saury's in season too.
確かに せっかくの
旬のサンマが…
はっ 旬の！
In season!
That's it.
（堂島）
そういうことだな
Because it's in season,
the Pacific saury won't be eclipsed.
旬のサンマなら
霞むどころか―
Rather, it has the potential to become a solid foundation for the entire dish.
料理全体の土台となる程の
ポテンシャルを持っている
He was able to select that dish precisely because
he has confidence in his ability to judge ingredients.
目利きに自信があるからこそ
あの料理を選択できたのだろうな
Above all, he's very calm.
それにしても 落ち着いている
I don't sense any nerves or eagerness toward the match in him.
決勝への緊張や気負いなど
全く感じない
Very impressive.
大したものだ
Of course you wouldn't, Chef Doujima.
当然ですわ 堂島シェフ
（堂島）んん？
Ryou-kun has faced me in cooking battles for a very long time now!
リョウ君は昔から私と
真剣勝負してきたんですもの
フフ…　懐かしいですね
Brings back memories.
You were both so young. Very cute, you was.
２人ともまだ幼き時代
可愛かったです
You knew him back when he was still in Scandinavia, Aunt Leonora.
北欧にいた時の彼を
ご存知ですものね
レオノーラおば様も
Granny?!
おばあ様？
How rude!
失礼です！
Showing off your youth! Selfish, Erina-chan!
己の若さ自慢するのこと
さもしいですよ えりなちゃん！
That's not what I said!
（えりな）違います！
"Aunt" and "Granny" are two different words!
“おば様”と“おばあ様”は
別の言葉です！
So this is the boy, Alice?
この子がそうなの？
アリス
Yes, Mother!
そうよ お母様
私のお付きにしようと思ってるの
I want to make him my aide!
Let go. I'm prepping.
放せ 仕込み中だ
Erina has a secretary now!
えりなにだって
秘書が付いたんでしょ？
I want an aide around my own age too!
私も同年代の
付き人がほしいの！
（黒木場の鳴き声）
（レオノーラ）そうねえ～
Well, we should ask your father.
パパにも聞いてみないと
Don't act like I'm not even here!
勝手に話進めんな！
I'm already the head chef of this restaurant!
俺はもうこの店で
トップ張ってんだ
I'm not gonna serve you—
お前の下に付く気なんか…
I believe I told you to call me "miss."
私のことは“お嬢様”って呼ぶよう
伝えたはずだけど？
Go home.
帰れ！
Then let's do a cooking battle.
それじゃあ料理勝負を
しましょう
Huh?
はあ？
If you lose, become my loyal dog.
（アリス）
あなたが負けたら
私の犬になりなさい
Woof, woof!
ワンワン！
はあああああああっ！
That little girl's dish was better.
（料理人Ａ）
そっちの嬢ちゃんの方が
うめえ…
（黒木場）なああっ…
Come on. Say "woof" for me.
（アリス）
ほら　“ワン”って
言ってごらんなさい
くうっ… もう１回
勝負しろおおおおっ！
Battle me one more time!
（アリス）クスス～
（黒木場）ぐぬぬうっ…
（客の歓声）
ぐああああああっ！
Two years after our first match,
（黒木場）
最初の勝負から２年
the moment's finally come!
ついに 来た…
I've won!
俺の勝ちだ！
（料理人たちの歓声）
His first victory!
（黒木場）はああっ…
（アリス）ううっ！
We'll face off again tomorrow!
明日も もう一度勝負よ！
Okay, Ryou-kun?!
いいわね リョウ君！
Fine... miss.
（黒木場）いいぜ
（黒木場）お嬢
（アリス）んっ？
I'll fight you any time.
（黒木場）
何度でも 勝負してやるよ
ウフフッ
（料理人たちの笑い声）
Then you'll be polite to me when I win next time?
じゃあ次 私が勝ったら
敬語を使うの いいわね？
No way!
っざけんな！
フフッ…
（創真）ん？
（葉山）あっ…
Heat-resistant film?
（葉山）耐熱フィルムか
What, it's not cling wrap?
へえ～ あれラップじゃねえのか
It's capable of withstanding heat of greater than 200°C, and cold down to -40°C.
（丸井）
200度を超える耐熱性と―
マイナス40度までの
耐冷性を持ち―
Food can be wrapped in it and cooked.
包んだままで加熱調理が可能な
フィルムシートだ
He's absorbed an arsenal of molecular gastronomy techniques from his battles with Alice.
（えりな）
アリスとの勝負の中で
吸収した―
分子ガストロノミー的引き出し
His cooking now is not something he'd think up
just from cooking in a port town pub.
今の黒木場君が作る料理は―
港町の酒場で料理していたのでは
着想し得ないものね
This is indicative of their whole
history working hard together.
２人が切磋琢磨(せっさたくま)してきた
歴史そのものなんだわ
Ryou-kun, don't lose, okay?
（アリス）
負けちゃダメよ　リョウ君
No need to remind me, miss.
（黒木場）
言われるまでもないですよ
お嬢
This film is the key to my dish!
このフィルムが 俺の料理の
カギになる
Hayama!
（黒木場）
葉山！　てめえをこいつで
今度こそ仕留める
I'll get you for sure this time!
The one who will stand at the top of this selection... will be me!
選抜の頂点に立つのは―
この俺だ！
The moon's halfway across the sky!
（田所恵(たどころめぐみ)）
月が 道のりの半分まで…
Less than an hour left now.
（水戸(みと)郁魅(いくみ)）
残り１時間を切った
Oh, look.
（吉野悠姫(よしのゆうき)）あっ 見て！
I'm done.
完成だ！
So first up is Kurokiba.
一番乗りは黒木場か
But...
しかし本当に…
Is that... really his dish?
あれが… 料理？
In a hurry, huh?
ずいぶん急いだじゃねえか
調理に見落としがなけりゃいいがな
Let's hope you didn't overlook anything in your dish.
Run your mouth while you still can.
今のうちに減らず口を叩いとけ
My dish will crush your weapon.
俺の品はてめえの武器を
圧殺する！
What's Kurokiba trying to do with that flimsy film?
（創真）
黒木場のやつ
何をやろうってんだ？
あんなペラペラな
フィルムでよぉ
Something you're very familiar with, I bet.
たぶん お前もよく
知ってることだぜ
ん？
Candidate Kurokiba will serve first!
まずは黒木場選手の
サーブです
The moon serves to illuminate the candidate
（堂島）
審査台へと進む選手を―
who is advancing toward the judges like a stage light.
月の舞台照明が照らす
It's as though the light is purifying the chef and his dish!
まるで 料理人とその者が出す品を
清めるかのように
Wow!
ワーオッ！
Still simmering inside the pouch!
袋の中でまだグツグツ
煮えてるです
Very piping hot!
すこぶる熱々ですね！
He's going to make the judges open the dish?
あのまま審査員に
開封させるのか？
Now, have a taste!
いざ！　実食である！
（堂島）あっ！
（堂島）
ぬうんっ！
Shrimp!
エビ ムール貝
アサリ そして サンマ！
Mussels!
Clams!
And Pacific saury!
I'm getting dragged into a torrent of different aromas!
怒涛(どとう)の香りグラデーションに
引きずり込まれる～！
（レオノーラ）
はああっ！　思わず顔が
ほころびま～す！
It's so good, my face is going slack!
（大泉･早乙女）
うおっ！　総帥が！
Director!
He's usually so stern, yet he's grinning!
あの厳格な総帥が
ニヤケておる！
It's "the grin"!
（早乙女）“おニヤケ”だ
Who knew we'd see the grin here?!
まさかおニヤケが飛び出すとは！
The ingredients are about the same as those in an acqua pazza,
（黒木場）
使う素材はアクアパッツアと
ほとんど同じだが―
but wrapping them in a heat-resistant film changes the dish's name.
耐熱フィルムに包んだことで―
この品の料理名は変わる！
It's a cartoccio!
“カルトッチョ”
My dish is Autumn Pacific Saury Cartoccio!
俺の出した料理は
“秋サンマのカルトッチョ”だ！
（創真）ああ…
He served an umami detonator in the semi-finals.
（創真）準決勝では
旨味の発火装置
He followed that up with an aroma detonator, I guess.
んで お次は 香りの発火装置で
来たってわけか
I see.
なるほどな
Go on! Taste it!
さあ　味わいな！
んん～っ！
So fresh! The Pacific saury's fat is meltingly sweet!
新鮮すぎて サンマの脂が
とろけるように甘いで～す！
The seafood ingredients are
all extraordinarily fresh!
（堂島）
超絶鮮度の魚介
たっぷりとした旨味！
There's more than enough umami!
Such power, sealing so much dynamic umami into this dish through sheer force...
これだけ豪快な旨味を
力ずくで閉じ込めるとは…
何という荒々しさ！
This is Kurokiba Ryou's true worth!
黒木場リョウの真骨頂だ！
The Pacific saury may be in season,
（堂島）しかし 旬とはいえ―
but how could he craft such richness in flavor with so little seasoning?
ほとんど調味料も使わず
これほどの濃厚さを…
Hm? What is this refreshing aroma?
んんっ？　爽やかな香り
海産物ではない！
It's not from seafood. It's...
これは！
It's from herbs.
ハーブの香気だ！
That's right!
そのとおり！
I added them to the packet when I wrapped the ingredient with the film.
フィルムに包む時
一緒に仕込んだのさ
I used this herb butter!
このハーブバターをな！
After softening butter at room temperature,
（えりな）
常温にして
柔らかくしたバターに―
he kneaded in finely chopped herbs, spices, and garlic.
細かく刻んだハーブやスパイス
ニンニクなどを練り込んだ物を―
The herb butter is complete after resting overnight in the fridge.
一晩冷蔵庫で寝かせれば
完成する
It melted gradually from the heat in the oven,
（黒木場）
コイツがオーブンの中の熱で
時間をかけて溶けていき―
and its richness and flavor
そのコクと風味が―
gradually seeped into the Pacific saury and other ingredients!
サンマや他の素材に
じっくりと染み渡る！
It gave an incredible boost
to the flavors and the fragrance!
（仙左衛門）
味にも香りにも―
超ド級のインパクトを
与えおった
It's a violence of flavor that is absolute!
徹底的なまでの味の暴力
It seems we'll see my mother's "baring."
どうやら出るようだわ
お母様の“おはだけ”が！
What?!
（悠姫）ういいいいっ？
（涼子）こんな公の場で？
In somewhere this public?
Seriously?!
マジか！
Th-That'd be really bad!
そっ… そそそそれは
ダメなんじゃ…
（４人の叫び声）
Huh?
（４人）ああっ？
What a wonderful Pacific saury dish.
素晴らしいサンマ料理でした
First, it had immediate visual impact upon arriving at the table.
まずテーブルに出された際の
ビジュアルの衝撃！
You have a firm grasp of the modern cooking trend that acknowledges the importance of a dish's aesthetics.
サーブの仕方も
料理の大切な要素と考える―
現代の調理トレンドを
しっかり踏襲しています
Given that the entire audience had leaned forward to look at the dish, your plan can be said to be a success.
会場中が前のめりになって
注目していたことからも―
その計画は見事に完遂したと
言えるでしょう
Anchovies are often used in acqua pazza, but not in this dish, since herb butter was used.
アクアパッツアには
アンチョビが使われることが多い…
When Mother eats something delicious, she sheds her broken
Japanese and "bares" a fluent command of the language.
お母様は おいしい品を食べると
片言がはだけて―
That was wise.
流暢(りゅうちょう)にしゃべり出すの
Adding both would have led to a clash of flavors.
Right, I remember.
そうだったわね…
The herb butter plays a critical role
in establishing this dish.
Shedding broken Japanese?
How's that work?!
片言がはだけるって 何？
The mellow butter serves to meld the flavors from each ingredient.
（レオノーラ）
バターのまろやかさは素材同士の
エキスを１つにまとめるのにも―
効果を発揮　しかしハーブによって
しつこく後を引くこともなく―
Its herbs impart a flavor that is strong, yet light and not overwhelming.
強烈な味のインパクトは
軽やかに通り抜け…
Flavors only made possible with Pacific saury in season, and no other fish!
（仙左衛門）
他のどの魚でもなく―
That further enhances the Pacific saury's aroma.
The heat-resistant film and herb butter both serve to take full advantage of the Pacific saury's flavors.
旬のサンマでなければ
成立しない一品
This is a culmination of his culinary techniques!
彼奴(きゃつ)の調理技術の集大成！
His singular focus in doing so is what made this dish's flavors possible!
Body...
（仙左衛門）身も！
（レオノーラ）心も！
...soul...
（堂島）海と
...and ocean!
All as one!
（３人）１つに！
Kurokiba, that's amazing!
（男子生徒Ｄ）
すげーぞ　黒木場ぁ！
The director went bare-chested, too!
（男子生徒Ｅ）
本家おはだけも出た～！
Well?!
（黒木場）
どうだ　俺の料理の膂力(りょりょく)を―
Sear my dish's power into your eyes, Hayama.
目に焼き付けろ 葉山！
ふう…
Next, Candidate Hayama will serve his dish!
（一色）
続いて葉山選手が
サーブします
（創真）ああっ？
（黒木場）ううっ…
The hell, asshole?!
（黒木場）
ふざけんな コラァ！
You think you can win against me
with that kind of dish?!
そんな品で俺に勝つ気かよ？
勝負を何だと思ってやがる！
Are you even being serious about this match?!
Forget it—
（黒木場）話にならねえ！
（葉山）お前は知らないんだ
You don't know that aroma can recreate even the philosophy behind a dish.
（葉山）
香りは 料理の概念すら
作り替えることを
It can't be.
（えりな）まさか―
A carpaccio?!
カルパッチョ？
An antipasto?!
（男子生徒Ｆ）
前菜メニュー？
No way!
（女子生徒Ａ）
ウソでしょ？
This is the grand finale!
（男子生徒Ｇ）決勝戦だぞ！
How can he win with an antipasto dish?
（男子生徒Ｈ）
前菜なんかで勝てるのかよ？
The antipasto is a dish intended to pique the diners' appetite at the start of a meal.
（えりな）
前菜はコース料理序盤で
客の食欲を開くための品
It is, by necessity, a lighter dish than others.
必然的に軽めのメニューとなる
Why did he choose that?
そんな料理を選ぶなんて…
Hayama!
（黒木場）
葉山 てめえの目利きの腕は
完全に俺と互角だ
Your ability to judge ingredients is equal to mine.
I bet you tried to take advantage of the best Pacific saury's fresh flavor in the raw,
最上級のサンマが誇る―
生ならではの新鮮な甘みを
生かそうとしたんだろうが
but there's no way your dish
can contend with my cartoccio.
旨味と香りの重厚な
インパクトで圧殺した―
Not after it crushed the judges
with its heavy umami and aroma!
俺のカルトッチョに
張り合えるわけがない！
（堂島）では 実食を…
（葉山）少々お待ちください
Well, let us taste—
Please wait a moment.
There's one last step.
（葉山）
最後の仕上げが
残っておりますので
He's searing the surface with a torch.
バーナーで炙(あぶ)って
表面に焼き目を？
But that'd hardly be enough to counter the Kurokiba boy's aroma detonator.
だが そんなことで黒木場少年の
香りの発火装置には―
到底及ば…
（創真）あっ
（黒木場）ハッ
うはっ ああ～っ！
（早乙女･大泉）
ぬおおおっ！
Done.
（葉山）完成
My dish is Seared Pacific Saury Carpaccio!
俺の料理は―
“炙りサンマのカルパッチョ”で
ございます
（観客の歓声）
Delicious.
（青木）うまい！
（佐藤）うまい！
Delicious!
It's delicious without even having a single taste!
（青木･佐藤）
食わなくてもうまい！
I can tell just how juicy it is!
ものすごいジューシーさが
伝わってくる！
It goes above and beyond what curing can do.
燻製(くんせい)を超える勢い…
（郁魅）お～っ！
（涼子）すごい！
Wow!
The dish became completely different
after the fish was seared.
炙る前と全然違う！
Sizzle!
じゅわああああああああっ！
It's as though the dish is seducing everyone who is about to taste it!
食事する者を なまめかしく
誘惑してくるようだわ
Oh!
もう… もう１秒も待てない…
I can't wait... another... second!
はふっ
あっ ああ～っ
ああ～ん はは～ん
The dressing consists of extra virgin olive oil, wine vinegar,
ドレッシングにはエキストラ
バージンオリーブオイルや―
ワインビネガー
and Pacific saury innards!
そしてサンマの肝を
和(あ)えている！
The rich flavor of the innards floods the tongue and emphasizes the sweetness of the Pacific saury's fat!
肝のコクが舌にじんわり染み渡り
サンマの脂の甘さを強調！
I'm drowning in the overflowing aromas and flavors!
溢れる香ばしさと風味で
溺れそう！
How many spices did you add to this dish?!
一体 どれだけ多くの
スパイスを組み合わせて…
Nay!
（仙左衛門）
いや！ 使用しているのは
オールスパイス ただ１つ
He has only used allspice!
What?!
何？
He only used one spice?
香辛料は１種類だけ？
I thought Hayama's special weapon was to weave various spices into the best aroma possible.
多種多様なスパイスで―
極上の香りを編みあげるのが
葉山の武器なんじゃ…
No.
（えりな）
違う　彼の香りを操る能力は―
His ability to manipulate fragrance is not just additive.
ただ足していくことに
留まらない
He was able to highlight the seasonal flavor of Pacific saury with vivid clarity
あえて香辛料を引くことで
旬のサンマの風味を―
by intentionally subtracting spices from the dish.
鮮明に浮かび上がらせることが
できたんだわ
And yet, how did he manage
such richness of fragrance?
それなのに
この香りの豊かさは何？
It's on par with the aromatic force
of Ryou-kun's cartoccio.
リョウ君のカルトッチョに
匹敵する勢いだった
Yes, and it's not possible to achieve that through searing alone!
ええ ただ炙っただけでは
ありえね～です！
フッ… “かえし”です
It's the kaeshi sauce.
I brushed it over the fish, right before serving.
サーブする直前に
身の表面にさっと塗りました
The kaeshi?
かえし？
つばめ返しですか？
Is that Tsubame Gaeshi?
Koujiro Sasaki?
コジロー･ササキ？
I'm surprised you know that word.
よく知っていますね
そんな言葉
But that's different.
でも違います
Kaeshi is a seasoning made by a mixture of soy sauce with mirin, sake,
かえしとは―
しょうゆに みりんや日本酒などを
加えて作る 合わせ調味料
and other ingredients.
You can make soba dipping sauce by diluting kaeshi with stock.
この かえしをだしで割ることで
そばつゆができるのです
It's considered an all-purpose seasoning for most Japanese dishes.
日本食全般に使える
万能調味料だとみなされていますわ
No wonder.
道理でな 魚の身はバーナーの
高い火力をもってしても―
Fish is hard to sear, even with
high heat from the torch.
焦げ目が付きづらいものなのだ
Kaeshi contains sugar, which makes the fish much easier to sear.
それが かえしに含まれる
糖分によって―
焦げやすくなる
So he prevented the loss of flavor
加熱が長引いて―
that would have resulted from a more prolonged exposure to heat.
新鮮なサンマの風味が
台無しになってしまうのも―
防いだということね
The surface fat of the fish
and the sugars in the kaeshi
（葉山）
サンマの表面の脂と
かえしの糖分が―
sizzle and bubble from the heat.
加熱によって
じゅわっと沸き立つ
In other words, I managed to demonstrate two theoretically opposing principles—
つまり俺は 香りの
“引き算”と“強調”
the subtraction of aroma and its emphasis—
in unison with this single dish.
相対(あいたい)する論理をこの一皿の上で
同時に披露したのです
Kurokiba Ryou and Hayama Akira.
（堂島）
黒木場リョウと葉山アキラ
They both evolved because of their previous match.
（仙左衛門）
一度ぶつかり合ったからこその
進化か
Kurokiba Ryou wields a massive sword.
黒木場リョウは肉厚の大剣を
振りかざす
He further improved the explosive, appetizing power of his dish at the finals.
決勝でも人の食欲を
引きずり出す爆発力を―
さらに高めて見せた
In contrast, the duck dish that Hayama Akira served at the semi-finals
（堂島）
対して 準決勝で
葉山アキラが出したカモ料理は―
was a brilliant feast of spices.
煌(きら)びやかなるスパイスの狂宴(きょうえん)
It was like a finely crafted, ornate sword.
さながら意匠と装飾が施された
宝剣だった！
But look at Hayama tonight.
（仙左衛門）
それが今宵の葉山はどうだ？
Refinement through differentiation and selection
選別 択一ゆえの洗練
has produced a blade that is as sharp and fine as a well-honed rapier!
鋭く細く研ぎ澄まされた
レイピアの如し！
（黒木場）うあああああっ！
（葉山）うっ…
（黒木場）ううっ！
（黒木場）オラアアアア！
（葉山）フウッ！
（黒木場）くっ… くっ…
What did you call me before?
A one-trick pony with spices?
（葉山）
スパイスしか能がない
ワンパターン―
This is what it means to have
absolute mastery over aroma.
だったか？
香りを従えるということは
こういうことだ
くうううっ！
So this is the master of fragrance,
Hayama Akira's, true worth!
（堂島）
これが香りの名手
葉山アキラの真骨頂か
This Pacific saury is such a pure force!
サンマの純粋なる威力
風味を真っ直ぐに―
It unleashes its flavor with no pretense!
A well-aimed arrow is true!
解き放つ！
正射必中！　お見事！
Bravo!
（観客の歓声）
The director's gone bare-chested again!
（男子生徒Ｉ）
本家おはだけ また出たぁ～！
Oh!
（恵）
ああっ！　月が隠れ始めてる！
The moon's starting to set!
創真君 急いで～！
Hurry, Souma-kun!
Yukihira, you're running out of time!
幸平！　時間ねえぞ～！
Sorry to keep you waiting.
（創真）お待ちどう！
This will be the finish!
こいつで〆(しめ)だっ！
おほっ！
フッフフ…
これは たまらないな
This is irresistible to anyone
who eats rice on a daily basis.
米を主食とする者ならば
条件反射で頬(ほお)がゆるむ―
It's enough to make you smile
purely from reflex...
from the sight of it and the destructive aroma!
見た目と香気の破壊力！
It's Salted Rice Bran Pacific Saury Rice.
“糠(ぬか)サンマの炊き込みご飯”っす
Salted rice bran?!
（男子生徒Ｊ）糠？
（女子生徒Ｂ）糠漬け？
Pickled with salted rice bran?!
So he didn't give up.
（男子生徒Ｋ）
諦めたんじゃなかったのかよ！
（郁魅･悠姫）おおおおっ！
It looks delicious!
おいしそう！
Well, I was thinking the worst case scenario when I saw that dull-looking Pacific saury.
いやあ～ あのモッサリな
サンマを見た時には―
どうなるかと思ったけどなぁ～
Yeah, I guess it looked dull because it'd been pickled in salted rice bran.
ああ なまくらに見えたのは―
サンマの糠漬けだったんだな！
（レオノーラ）お～っ！
I can't bear the piping hot fragrance!
炊き立ての香り
たまりませ～ん！
Yes, yes.
（創真）
はいは～い すぐによそいますんで
ちょっとお待ちくださいっす
I'll serve you right away.
Please wait just a moment.
Oh, Yukihira-kun!
もう 幸平君 いけずです！
早く早く！
What a tease! Hurry!
The other two were also creative about heightening our expectations,
（大泉）
他の２人もそれぞれ期待を高める
演出を仕掛けていたが―
but Yukihira Souma is not taking a back seat to them!
幸平創真も また然(しか)り！
He knows how to make his guests eager for his dish!
客の期待を煽(あお)る術―
心得ておる！
Here it comes!
来た来た！
やっとですね～！
Finally!
Now, let's taste!
いざ 実食です！
ふー　ふー　はふっ
ふうっ ふうっ
ほふ ほふ ほふ
はあああああんっ！
The happiness of Pacific saury brought by autumn
is spreading throughout my body!
秋がもたらすサンマの幸せが
体中に沁(し)み入る！
What gentle flavor!
何という やわらかなうまさ
He grilled the fish on a
clay cooking stove first—
サンマを七輪で一度焼いて…
He grilled it first,
then cooked it with the rice!
一度焼いてから
ご飯と一緒に炊き込む！
Such meticulous prep work allowed this much of the Pacific saury's aroma to transfer to the rice!
そうした細かい仕事によって―
ここまで見事に香ばしさが
ご飯に移っているわけです
And the Pacific saury itself is marvelous too!
そしてサンマがまた素晴らしい！
With every bite, the deep umami and fragrant aroma bursts forth from the saltiness into your mouth!
塩気の中にある深い旨味と
フワッと香る風味が―
噛みしめる度に
口の中に広がります！
This is on par with the Pacific saury in the other two's dishes!
他の２名に勝るとも
劣らない品質です！
Is this deep flavor due to the salted rice bran?!
この厚みのある味が
糠サンマというものなのですか？
Indeed. It's a traditional favorite from Hokkaido.
（堂島）
いかにも　北海道で古くから
親しまれてきた伝統食
The salted rice bran draws out an ingredient's umami,
removes any bad smells, and improves the nutritional value.
素材の旨味を引き出し
臭みも取って栄養価もアップする
Some insist that it is the best
preparation for Pacific saury.
最もうまくサンマを食う方法だと
言い切る者もいるほど
Still, I'm impressed you managed to improve the flavor to this degree, Yukihira.
それにしても
よくぞここまで味を高めたな
幸平
I took a big risk. It was a race against time!
イチかバチか
時間との勝負でしたわ
I bought as many high-quality Pacific saury from the fish market as I could
魚河岸で上等なサンマを
できる限り買い込んで―
試作をやりながら
熟成を繰り返しました
and kept testing aging methods.
Of course, I tried and improved other aging methods than salted rice bran too.
もちろん糠漬け以外の熟成も試して
改良しながらね
It was hard to make something that could compete with top-quality Pacific saury in season,
なかなか旬の上物に
対抗できるものは―
できなかったけど
but I finally found one that was satisfactory right before the match.
本番直前―
やっと満足いく熟成具合に
届いたのが―
That was this fish, aged using salted rice bran!
この糠漬け熟成だったんす
Hints from Fumio-san's words, the salted rice bran pickles at the dorm,
（創真）
ふみ緒さんの言葉や
寮で仕込んでた糠漬け
all the tips and tricks about aging
I learned from my friends...
みんなからもらった
熟成のノウハウ
All of it contributed to my inspiration!
その全部が
この閃(ひらめ)きにつながった！
He discovered that aging method on his own?!
あの熟成法に自力で
辿り着いたというのか！
Though we thought it
was a worthless blade,
なまくらかと思いきや―
it has shown itself to be a fine sword!
とんだ名刀が―
姿を現した！
Just like a swordsmith who forges
steel into a fine blade,
鉄を鍛えて名刀を生み出す
刀工のように―
he has created that sword of autumn on his own!
あの“秋の刀”を
彼自身が育てたのだ！
（観客の歓声）
♪～
seki wo kitta nodo kara te ga deru hodo
An intensely burning desire burst forth
hoshiku nattan da boku ja nai betsu no dareka
But not from me, from someone else
yume to kibou hoka ni nani ga iru to
Where's the me who believed that
omoeta koro no boku wa ima izuko e?
All one needs is to have hopes and dreams
nagai mono ni makarete ushinatta michishirube
Wrapped around something long, my compass was lost
sei to shi no hazama ni wa sunoo duroppu ga sakimidareru
On the border of life and death, snow drops bloom
nanika no machigai de kudakechitte shimatta nara
If by some mistake they get smashed
semete boku no nukegara ni hanataba wo soete
At least put flowers on the empty husk
konna mon ka na konna mon deshou
Is that the way things are? Yes, it is
akirame da to omowaretatte kamawanai kedo
You can call it resignation if you want
boku rashiku nai boku rashiku nai
But that's not me, that's not me
dare ni mo datte tsukureru mon ni kachi wa nai
There's no value in something just anyone could make
～♪
（観客の歓声）
Souma-kun's amazing!
すごいよ 創真君！
Yeah! No complaints here!
ああ 文句なしだぜ！
I bet he'll get high marks for that!
あれならきっと高評価を…
Oh!
ああっ！　総帥が…
はだけてない！
The director hasn't gone bare-chested!
H-Hey.
（男子生徒Ｌ）お おい…
（男子生徒Ｍ）ああ…
Yeah.
Right.
（男子生徒Ｎ）うん…
Chef Doujima and Ms. Leonora have also already rested their chopsticks!
（丸井）
堂島シェフとレオノーラ女史も
もう箸を置いてる
That means...
ってことは…
Hm...
（大泉）
うーん…
Did the Yukihira boy spend too much time trying to close the ingredient quality gap?
目利きの差を埋めることに
時間を取られ過ぎたか 幸平少年
In terms of creativity, his dish
is not on par with those two!
料理のアイデアでは
２人に届いておらん！
Of course he couldn't hope to compete with them.
（女子生徒Ｃ）
やっぱり あの２人に敵うわけ…
Yeah.
（男子生徒Ｏ）だよなぁ～
Like I thought, the match will be between...
（女子生徒Ｄ）
予想どおり優勝を争うのは…
Kurokiba and Hayama!
（男子生徒Ｐ）
黒木場と葉山！
I'd like you to have seconds too.
おかわりも食べて
ほしいんすけど―
Does no one want more?
まだ食べたい人
いないっすか？
It's the end of the line.
ここまで… だな
Souma-kun!
創真君…
With this, we conclude the evaluation—
ただ今をもって
審査を終了と…
If it means you'd have seconds,
（創真）
おかわりして頂けるなら―
I'd like you to pour this over the rice and dig in.
こいつを注いで食べてもらおうと
思ってんすけど
Hm!
（仙左衛門）むう！
（レオノーラ）はっ…
（堂島）うっ…
（葉山）あっ…
（黒木場）ええっ
My Pacific saury dish...
（創真）
俺の サンマ料理はまだ―
is not yet complete.
完成してないんすよ
I'll show you this blade's real edge!
（創真）
この刀の ほんとの切れ味―
お見せします！
NEXT TIME
A NEW GENIUS
Next time, "A New Genius."